It’s Professor Dave, let’s learn the distance
formula.
As we navigate the coordinate plane in our
algebraic adventures, one thing we might want
to do is find the distance between two points.
Luckily, we are well equipped to do this,
since we know the Pythagorean Theorem.
If you need to review it, check out the tutorials
on how to use the theorem, as well as how
the theorem was derived, in the geometry portion
of this playlist.
Otherwise, let’s just select two points
in the coordinate plane, and draw a line between them.
The length of this line is what we are trying
to figure out, and in order to get it, we
can make a right triangle.
This line will be the hypotenuse, and the
legs will be the horizontal and vertical line
segments we need to construct the triangle.
Now let’s label the hypotenuse as D, the
distance we want to know.
The legs can be expressed as the difference
between the respective points that mark their ends.
This horizontal line segment has a length
of X two minus X one, since it only moves
in the X direction.
The vertical line segment has a length of
Y two minus Y one, since it only moves in
the Y direction.
Now, we just use the Pythagorean Theorem.
The square of this leg plus the square of
the other leg equals the hypotenuse squared,
or D squared.
Then, all we do is take the square root of
both sides to solve for D.
We will only take the positive value here,
as negative length doesn’t make any sense.
And there you have it, we have derived the
distance formula.
Let’s give it a shot.
Take the points negative two, two, and two,
five.
What is the distance covered by the line segment
that connects these two points?
Well, let’s take our X values and our Y
values, and plug them into the formula.
That gives us four, which squared is sixteen,
and three, which squared is nine.
Add them up and we get twenty-five, take the
square root, and that gives us five for the
distance.
This is the same value we would get if we
contructed a triangle and performed the Pythagorean
Theorem.
So the distance formula is a generalized way
to simply plug in the coordinates of two points,
and find the distance between them.
Let's check comprehension.